<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE reference 
[<!ENTITY % isogrk1 PUBLIC "ISO 8879:1986//ENTITIES Greek Letters//EN//XML"
                    "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xmlcharent/0.3/iso-grk1.ent">
 <!ENTITY % isopub PUBLIC "ISO 8879:1986//ENTITIES Publishing//EN//XML"
                    "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xmlcharent/0.3/iso-pub.ent">
%isogrk1;
%isopub;
]>

<glossary id="input_options" xmlns='http://docbook.org/ns/docbook' xml:lang="en" xmlns:et="http://super-resolution.de/elemtable">
   <title>Input options</title>

   <glossdiv>
      <title>Input fields</title>
      <et:elem desc="Number of input channels" topic="join.ChannelCount">
            This field is used to declare how many <xref 
                  linkend="input_channels">input channels</xref> should be
            made available. New input channel configuration tabs are added
            or removed as needed when this field is changed. It might take
            rapidSTORM a moment to do this, please have patience.
      </et:elem>
      <et:elem desc="Input type" topic="InputType">
            This field is used to select the general type of input that should
            be used. If input should be read from any kind of file, select
            "input from a file" here and the specific type of file in the 
            <xref linkend="FileType"/> field.
      </et:elem>
      <et:elem desc="Input file" topic="InputFile">
            The location of the input data is selected in this field. You can put
            any existing file here. It's interpretation (file type) and file-specific
            input options are set in the <xref linkend="FileType"/> field.
            This field is only available when you have selected "File" as <xref linkend="InputType">input type</xref>.
      </et:elem>
      <glossentry id="FileType">
         <glossterm>File type</glossterm>
         <glossdef><para>
               This field is used to select the type of data that are present in the
               input file. Usually, this is auto-detected, and when the 
               <xref linkend="InputFile">input file</xref> location is changed, this
               field is updated with the auto-determined file type for the selected
               input file.
         </para></glossdef>
      </glossentry>
      <et:elem desc="Join inputs on" topic="join.JoinOn">
            When multiple channels are selected, this field is used to declare how these
            multiple channels are combined into a single image or dataset. The available options are:
            <orderedlist>
            <listitem>Spatial joining in X/Y dimension, which means that images or datasets are pasted
            next to each other. For spatial joining of image data in the X/Y dimension, the not-joined dimension
            (e.g. the Y dimension for X joining) must match.</listitem>
            <listitem>Spatial joining in Z dimension. When processing images, each input channel is 
               considered as a separate layer, with the first channel forming the first layer. For
               localization data, this is identical to X/Y joining in Z dimension.</listitem>
            <listitem>Joining in time. Channels are processed after each other in the sequence of their
               declaration. For images, the dimensions of the images must match.</listitem>
            </orderedlist>
      </et:elem>
      <et:elem desc="Output file basename" topic="OutputBasename">
            This is the location and filename prefix for rapidSTORM output files. More precisely,
            the filenames for rapidSTORM's output files are produced by adding a file-specific suffix
            to the value of this field. 
      </et:elem>
      <et:elem desc="Fluorophore types" topic="FluorophoreTypeCount">
            The number of <xref linkend="fluorophore"/>s present in the input should be given here.
            When multiple fluorophores are selected, additional input fields will appear and allow
            configuration of the spectral parameters.
      </et:elem>
      <et:elem desc="Size of one input pixel" topic="PixelSize">
      </et:elem>
      <et:elem desc="PSF FWHM" topic="PSF.FWHM">
            The full width at half maximum of the optical point spread function. More
            precisely, the typical width of an emitter should be entered here, including fluorophore
            size and camera pixelation effects. rapidSTORM will fit spots in the images with a Gaussian 
            with the same FWHM as given here. If the PSF is unknown, it can be determined semi-automatically
            by using the <xref linkend="estimate_psf_form"/> output.
      </et:elem>
      <et:elem desc="3D PSF model" topic="3DType">
            The 3D PSF model denotes the functional form of the PSF's change with respect to the 
            emitter's Z position. See <xref linkend="threedforms"/> for possible values.
      </et:elem>
   </glossdiv>

   <glossdiv>
      <title>Choices for <xref linkend="FileType"/></title>

      <et:elem desc="Localizations file" topic="localizations_file_input">
      This input driver can be used to read the files written
         by the <xref linkend="localizations_file_output"/> output module.
         The file format is documented with the output module.
      </et:elem>

      <glossentry>
         <glossterm>Andor SIF file</glossterm>
         <glossdef>
            <para>This input driver can read the Andor SIF file format produced
               by Andor Technology software such as SOLIS.</para>
            <para>SIF files are stored in an uncompressed binary format with a
               simple text header. Because reading SIF files cannot be implemented
               in a forward-compatible way (reading new SIF files with old software),
               this driver might be unable to open the file; in this case, an error
               message is shown indicating the maximum known and the encountered
               version of the Andor SIF structure. Please obtain a newer version
               of this software in this case.</para>
            <para>If the <xref linkend="expertise_level"/> is
               sufficient, this module allows to select an inclusive range of
               image numbers (starting from 0) which are selected from the SIF file.
               This range is automatically cropped to the range of available images.
            </para>
         </glossdef>
      </glossentry>
   </glossdiv>

</glossary>

