<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>

<book xmlns='http://docbook.org/ns/docbook' version="5.0" xml:lang="en" status="draft">
<title>rapidSTORM 2 manual</title>
<bookinfo>
    <legalnotice>
        <para>
    Copyright (c)  2012 Steve Wolter, Sven Proppert
    Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document
    under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License, Version 1.3
    or any later version published by the Free Software Foundation;
    with no Invariant Sections, no Front-Cover Texts, and no Back-Cover Texts.
    A copy of the license is included in the section entitled "GNU
    Free Documentation License".
        </para>
    </legalnotice>
    <author><firstname>Steve</firstname><surname>Wolter</surname></author>
    <author><firstname>Sven</firstname><surname>Proppert</surname></author>
</bookinfo>
<preface>
    <title>Motivation and scope of rapidSTORM</title>

    <para>
        The rapidSTORM software is a single-molecule localization microscopy evaluation software.
        Its aim is to identify single fluorophores in sequences of images of sparsely emitting samples.
        Such images are generated by techniques such as dSTORM, STORM, PALM and FPALM and are used there to achieve super-resolution imaging.
        Since a sequence usually consists of several thousand images and nanometre precision is necessary for super-resolution, computational speed and precision are both extremely important.
        Delivering these attributes is the goal of rapidSTORM.
    </para>
    <para>
        rapidSTORM aims to support both three-dimensional imaging and spectral unmixing applications.
        Three-dimensional imaging refers to the computation of individual fluorophore's Z positions via the observation of shape changes in the point spread function.
        Both astigmatic and multi-layer approaches are supported here.
        Spectral unmixing refers to distinguishing multiple fluorophore types by their differential emission strength in multiple optical detection paths.
        For example, a dichroic mirror might be used to project the red part of the fluorescence on one camera and the blue part on a second camera.
    </para>
    <para>
        rapidSTORM is not meant as an all-purpose evaluation tool for super-resolution microscopy or as a camera driver.
        It is, however, designed to play nice with other systems and has a good number of evaluation options built in.
        You are encouraged to interface the direct camera input driver with a camera system or use 
        the different output options for necessary control systems.
    </para>
</preface>

<preface>
    <title>Help on Help</title>
    <para>This manual consists of the following parts:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><xref linkend="UI"/> gives a broad overview over the dialogs
            and general usage of this software. An example of basic usage is included.</listitem>
        <listitem><xref linkend="Step_by_Step"/> consists of concise, step-by-step
            descriptions of typical nontrivial usage patterns.</listitem>
        <listitem><xref linkend="input_options"/> documents the various input and output
            modules and their options in detail.</listitem>
        <listitem><xref linkend="output_modules"/> documents the various input and output
            modules and their options in detail.</listitem>
        <listitem><xref linkend="Fundamentals"/> discusses fundamental concepts and 
            file formats in depth.</listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>It is recommended to read <xref linkend="UI"/> first to get a broad overview over the user interface.
      Further information can be found in the relevant reference sections, which can be studied in any order.</para>
</preface>
  
<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="ui.xml"/>
<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="usage-examples.xml"/>
<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="input-options.xml"/>
<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="output-options.xml"/>
<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="errors.xml"/>
<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="fundamentals.xml"/>

<bibliography id="Bibliography">
  <title>Bibliography</title>
  <biblioentry id="WolterDiplomarbeit">
    <abbrev>Wolter2009a</abbrev>
    <title>An accurate and efficient algorithm for real-time localisation
         of photoswitchable fluorophores</title>
    <author>
      <firstname>Steve</firstname>
      <surname>Wolter</surname>
    </author>
    <publisher>
      <publishername>Bielefeld University</publishername>
    </publisher>
    <date>2009</date>
    <bibliosource class="uri">http://bieson.ub.uni-bielefeld.de/opus/frontdoor.php?source_opus=1494</bibliosource>
  </biblioentry>
  <biblioentry id="Wolter_JoM_09">
    <abbrev>Wolter2009b</abbrev>
  </biblioentry>
  <biblioentry id="ThompsonPaper">
    <abbrev>Thompson2002</abbrev>
  </biblioentry>
  <biblioentry id="Huang2008">
    <abbrev>Huang2008</abbrev>
    <authorgroup>
      <author>
        <surname>Huang</surname>
        <firstname>Bo</firstname>
      </author>
      <author>
        <surname>Wang</surname>
        <firstname>Wenqin</firstname>
      </author>
      <author>
        <surname>Bates</surname>
        <firstname>Mark</firstname>
      </author>
      <author>
        <surname>Zhuang</surname>
        <firstname>Xiaowei</firstname>
      </author>
    </authorgroup>
    <title>Three-Dimensional Super-Resolution Imaging by Stochastic Optical Reconstruction Microscopy</title>
    <citetitle pubwork="journal">Science</citetitle>
    <pagenums>810--813</pagenums>
    <pubdate>February 2008</pubdate>
    <volumenum>319</volumenum>
    <issuenum>5864</issuenum>
  </biblioentry>
</bibliography>
</book>
