<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter 
[<!ENTITY % isogrk1 PUBLIC "ISO 8879:1986//ENTITIES Greek Letters//EN//XML"
                    "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xmlcharent/0.3/iso-grk1.ent">
 <!ENTITY % isopub PUBLIC "ISO 8879:1986//ENTITIES Publishing//EN//XML"
                    "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xmlcharent/0.3/iso-pub.ent">
%isogrk1;
%isopub;
]>


<chapter xmlns='http://docbook.org/ns/docbook' id="UI" xml:lang="en" xmlns:et="http://super-resolution.de/elemtable">
   <title>User interface</title>

<section>
    <title>Basic use tutorial</title>
    <task id="tutorial_start">
        <title>Start an evaluation</title>
        <taskprerequisites>
            This tutorial will exemplify basic rapidSTORM usage by showing
            how to convert an Andor SIF acquisition to a super-resoluted image
            with rapidSTORM. We will load an Andor SIF file, characterize the
            optics by giving a pixel size and the PSF full width at half maximum,
            give a target image resolution and start an evaluation.
        </taskprerequisites>
        <procedure>
            <step>Start rapidSTORM via the icon in the Start menu</step>
            <step>Select the input file by dragging &amp; dropping it from a
                Windows Explorer window to the <et:elemref linkend="InputFile"/>
                field (<xref linkend="example-screenshot.input-file"/>.</step>
            <step>Set the input pixel size by entering the value in the <xref linkend="PixelSizeInNM"/>
            field (<xref linkend="example-screenshot.pixel-size"/>).</step>
            <step>Enter the full width at half maximum of your point spread function into
                the <et:elemref linkend="PSF"/> field (<xref linkend="example-screenshot.psf-fwhm"/>. You can estimate this value from
                the numerical aperture of your microscope by the approximation <inlineequation>
                    <mathphrase>&lgr; / 2 NA</mathphrase></inlineequation>, where &lgr; is
                    the detection wavelength and NA the numerical aperture of your objective.</step>
            <step>Show the options of the image display output by clicking on it 
                  (<xref linkend="example-screenshot.image-display"/>) in the output option tree.</step>
            <step>Optionally change the resolution of the result image by changing the resolution
                fields (<xref linkend="example-screenshot.resolution-x"/>).</step>
            <step>Start the computation by clicking the <guilabel>Run</guilabel> button (<xref linkend="example-screenshot.run"/>).</step>
        </procedure>
        <taskrelated>
            <informalfigure  id="basic_window_screenshot">
                <screenshot>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobjectco>
                            <areaspec>
                                <area id="example-screenshot.input-file" coords="300,300 400,400"/>
                                <area id="example-screenshot.pixel-size" coords="300 400"/>
                                <area id="example-screenshot.psf-fwhm" coords="300 400"/>
                                <area id="example-screenshot.image-display" coords="300 400"/>
                                <area id="example-screenshot.resolution-x" coords="300 400"/>
                                <area id="example-screenshot.run" coords="300 400"/>
                            </areaspec>
                            <imageobject>
                                <imagedata fileref="rapidstorm-step-by-step-2.PNG" width="100%"/>
                            </imageobject>
                        </imageobjectco>
                    </mediaobject>
                </screenshot>
            </informalfigure>
            <para>After you finished starting the evaluation, a new tab will appear in the job tab bar,
                  and a new window will be opened. Continue with the next task: <xref linkend="tutorial_jobwindow"/>.</para>
        </taskrelated>
    </task>
    <task id="tutorial_jobwindow">
        <title>Manage an evaluation</title>
        <taskprerequisites>
            This tutorial shows how to interpret the job window and to modify the output image.
            We assume you have started a job, as described in the <xref linkend="tutorial_start"/>
            tutorial.
        </taskprerequisites>
        <procedure>
            <step>Enhance the image contrast by raising the <xref linkend="Viewer_Status_Power"/> value
                to 0.5. Note how the intensity key next to
                the image display window changes.</step>
            <step>Filter out low-intensity localizations by checking the box next to 
                <xref linkend="ExpressionFilter_LowerAmplitudeThreshold"/> and entering a value of
                4500. Filtering out weak localizations reduces background noise and enhances the
                image resolution slightly, but reduces the number of localizations available for
                image construction.</step>
            <step>Change the colour code by changing <xref linkend="Viewer_ColorScheme"/> to 
                <guilabel>Vary hue with coordinate value</guilabel>. The color of the image now
                shows the X coordinate, resulting in a rainbow-coloured image.</step>
            <step>Change the hue-producing coordinate by changing <guilabel>Coordinate to vary hue with</guilabel>
                to <guilabel>emission strength</guilabel>. The colour code would now display the intensity
                of each localization, but stays grey because the range is not set.</step>
            <step>Change the <guilabel>Color range</guilabel> fields at the lower right end of the result
                image window to 5000 and 30000 by entering each value and pressing enter.</step>
            <step>Close the job by pressing <guilabel>Close job</guilabel>. The image window will stay active until
                it is closed.</step>
        </procedure>
    </task>
</section>

   <para>The graphical user interface for rapidSTORM consists of two
      windows: The <xref linkend="configuration_window"/>
      is used to set the parameters for dSTORM processing
      and monitor the progress of computation. The 
      <indexterm><primary>configuration window</primary></indexterm>
      configuration window
      is opened when rapidSTORM is started. The second window is the
      <xref linkend="image_window"/>, which shows the current dSTORM result
      image and allows the user to scroll and zoom the image.</para>

   <section id="configuration_window">
      <title>Configuration window</title>
      <para>The <indexterm><primary>configuration window</primary></indexterm>
        configuration window is the main window of rapidSTORM
        and consists of three parts: From top to bottom, there is the
        menu bar, the job bar and the configuration area.</para>
      <para>The latter is the area that takes up most of the screen and contains
        a number of configuration items, which are text fields or drop-down
        boxes used to set the rapidSTORM parameters. While the meaning of these
        boxes is explained later in this chapter, their operation is 
        standardized. The text fields allow to enter texts or, in most cases,
        numbers. If the field is meant for a filename, a select button
        is provided next to the text field, and the user may also drag and
        drop files to the field. If the field is numeric and has known limits,
        a slider is shown next to it; operating the slider or turning the
        mouse wheel can be used to change the field's value.</para>
      <para>The rest of this chapter will define the meaning of the fields.
       It starts with an explanation of the job
       concept and the job bar and continue with the
       different views in the configuration area and the menu bar.</para>
      <section>
        <title>rapidSTORM jobs</title>
        <para>Each file or direct acquisition processed with rapidSTORM,
          together with the computation options used for it, is
          called a <indexterm><primary>job</primary></indexterm>job in
          rapidSTORM
          parlance. Jobs are computed independently from each other, and
          you can have multiple jobs open at once if your computer memory
          permits. The currently open jobs are displayed in
          the <indexterm><primary>job bar</primary></indexterm>job bar near
          the top of the configuration window.</para>
        <para>The job bar is also used to select which job's status to show.
          Click on a tab to change the currently visible job.</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>The job options tab</title>
        <para><indexterm><primary>job options</primary></indexterm>
           When the rapidSTORM program is started, one tab in the job bar
           called "job options" is already present. This tab does not represent
           a job, but rather displays the configuration options for new jobs.
           </para>
        <para>The job option pane is organized along the flow of data from input
           file to result: Options that show up at the top of the job options list
           refer to pre-processing, and those towards the bottom refer to output
           configuration and post-processing.</para>
        <para>When the job option tab is selected, the configuration area
          consists of four major elements:</para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem><para>The <guilabel>Input options</guilabel> box is used to 
              select the input files and provide information about the used
              optics. Its elements are described in <xref linkend="input_options"/>.</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>The <guilabel>Choose engine</guilabel> box allows the
                selection of a processing engine. The <guilabel>rapidSTORM engine</guilabel>
                option will try to localize fluorophores in the given images, and
                the <guilabel>Replay stored localizations</guilabel> choice reads
                pre-computed localizations from a file. The options for the 
                <guilabel>rapidSTORM engine</guilabel> choice are described in
                <xref linkend="engine_options"/>.</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>The <xref linkend="output_options"/> box controls
              how the extracted localizations are filtered, displayed
              and stored.</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>The run button starts a new job with the currently
              selected options. The configuration items for the job option tab
              can be changed while the started job is running and have no effect
              on it.</para></listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        <section id="output_options" xreflabel="Output Options">
           <title>Output options</title>
            <figure id="output_box">
               <title>Output options box</title>
               <mediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                     <imagedata fileref="rapidstorm-output-box.PNG" width="100%"/>
                  </imageobject>
               </mediaobject>
            </figure>
           <para>The output options box is separated into two components:
             <indexterm><primary>output tree</primary></indexterm>
             To the left hand side, you see a tree element showing the
             <emphasis>output tree</emphasis>. The output tree is the data
             structure that controls the filtering
             and processing of the localizations found by the engine. On the
             right hand side, you see the
             options for the currently selected node in the output tree. When
             the program is started, this is the root node.</para>
           <para>The output tree defines the way in which localizations are
             processed. Each node of the tree is called an
             <indexterm><primary>output module</primary></indexterm>
             <emphasis>output module</emphasis> (in this section also called
             module), which processes data in some
             way specific to the type of the module: For example, the
             "Count localizations" module counts all localizations it 
             receives and displays the current amount.</para>
           <para>The first, root node (called "dSTORM engine output")
             symbolizes the output of the <xref linkend="dSTORM_engine"/>.
             Each module connected to it receives all localizations found by
             the engine without filtering or processing.</para>
           <para>Some modules such as <xref linkend="ExpressionFilter"/>
             not only receive, but also send localizations. For example, the
             localization filter sends all localizations that match its
             criteria. The outputs that receive localizations from such a
             filter are displayed in the tree as children nodes of it.</para>
           <para>For an example, consider
             the tree shown in the graphic: 
             While the first "Localizations file", "Count localizations",
             "Display progress", "Filter localizations" and "Average images"
             receive the unmodified output from the 
             <xref linkend="dSTORM_engine"/>. The
             localizations received by the second "Localizations file" and for
             "Image display" are those modified by the "Filter localizations"
             module.</para>
          <para>Clicking on an output module in the tree view shows this
             module's configuration in the right part of the display. Each 
             module has specific configuration options, which are documented
             together with the module's description in the <xref linkend="output_modules"/> chapter.
             For modules that can have outputs, you can manage the suboutputs
             by the following standard control elements:</para>
          <et:elemtable> 
            <title>Output configuration items</title>
            <et:elem desc="Choose new output" topic="ChooseOutput">
              In this list you find all available output modules.
              After selecting one of the modules, it is added into the
              output tree as a child of the current tree node.
            </et:elem>
            <et:elem desc="Select output to remove" topic="ToRemove">
              Select one of the active outputs of the current module in
              this box. The selected module and all of its submodules are
              deleted from the output tree.
            </et:elem>
          </et:elemtable>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>The job status tabs</title>
        <para>For each running job, a job status tab is displayed in the job
            bar. Some output modules such as <xref linkend="image_display"/>
            display control and information elements in the job status tab,
            in the same order as they appear in the output tree.</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>The menu bar</title>
        <para>The menu bar is the control element at the top of the 
          configuration window and offers two controls: Storing and loading
          macros and changing the expertise level.
        </para>
        <section><title>Macros</title>
        <para>Macros are text files that can be used to automatically repeat
          the actions youhave performed in the configuration window. This
          feature can save a great amount of work if you often use a particular
          configuration that is tedious to set up.</para>
        <para>You can set up a
          macro by selecting the <guimenuitem>Save as ...</guimenuitem> item in
          the <guimenu>Macro</guimenu> menu. After you have saved your macro, you
          can continue work normally; should you wish to re-save your workflow,
          use the <guimenuitem>Save</guimenuitem> or <guimenuitem>Save as ...</guimenuitem>
          items.</para>
        <para>To replay a macro, open a fresh instance of the rapidSTORM 
          software, select the <guimenuitem>Load</guimenuitem> menu item and the macro
          you want to replay.</para>
        </section>
        <section id="expertise_level">
          <title>Changing the expertise level</title> 
          <para>Not all controls are shown at the start of the rapidSTORM
          software to avoid confusion for new users. To display more 
          configuration options, the <guimenu>Expertise</guimenu> menu is used.
          The expertise level influences only which elements are displayed,
          not the result of any computation.
          </para>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section id="image_window">
      <title>Image window</title>
        <para>When a job is started with the <xref linkend="image_display"/>
            output module active, a window showing an image with the already
            computed localizations is displayed.</para>
        <para>The image display window shows one or two keys on its right side.
            If there is one key, it shows the mapping of intensity values, i.e.
            accumulated emission intensities, to colors. The numbers are suffixed
            with SI unit prefixes, and the unit is displayed at the top of the
            key.</para>
        <para>If the image is hued by coordinate, a second key appears. The left
            key is in black and white and shows the image intensity, while the right key
            shows a color spectrum and displays the values indicated by the colours.
            The two text boxes at the bottom of the right key allow setting the range
            of the hueing. If the right key is completely black, the range is unknown
            and must be entered.</para>
    </section>
</chapter>
